<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>wandrr</title>
    <description>This is a blog about travel and tech.
</description>
    <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 16:47:25 -0800</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 16:47:25 -0800</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.6</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>New stuff to learn</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Before delving into another new things to learn, I wanted to write a recap of what I’ve been doing lately. Can’t really include all details but atleast write a summary of my experience.
You can read further if your interested. I blog to keep track of my learning progress about the web, I consider these as my personal note, but I don’t mind sharing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wordpress-and-static-sites&quot;&gt;Wordpress and Static Sites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve worked with alot of wordpress websites as sideline job and with designers and other developers. I noticed that everyone has their opinion about methods of how a work should get done. One important thing is, we should be able to deliver the product. It doesn’t matter how it is built, as long as it works, its good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When to code from scratch and when NOT to.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I am a fan of coding things from scratch. I take into consideration how a website/application is built. But coding from scratch is not worth it when its just for sideline.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Things to note though are:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Plugins save my projects! lol&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Follow how Wordpress, plugins work rather than customizing a workflow from scrtach.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning Woocommerce with a Fancy Product Designer plugin&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Came across a project that requires online sales, so we decided to use Woocommerce.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Components of a E-commerce website are:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Products have different variations&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Shipping&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Payment Gateway&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;again, Plugins are my hero! rather than delving into APIs&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Static site generator&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Static sites are great alternative to wordpress if a website doesn’t require E-commerce. But it does require learning curve for non-techie users.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Since static sites are new, it may not be prone to hackers like wordpress&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Example tools are:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Grav - a PHP site generator, has a really nice optional Admin dashboard.&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Jekyll - love it coz Github uses it, and you can easily publish your site for free. But doesn’t have a nice Admin Dashboard like Grav.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;front-end-tools-and-npm-community&quot;&gt;Front-End tools and NPM community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I just found out not all developers agree to the whole NPM community trend. IMO though, I love workflows and how easy it is to code with these tools. I love learning at the sametime, so I guess I fit into this type of development preference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gulp.js and the whole NPM community.&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Gulp.js was the first built tool I learned. IMO, its an important tool so we can use other JavaScript/Front-End tools such as:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Template engines&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;JS transpilers&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;JS compilers&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;CSS compilers&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;workflow automation&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;testing&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;and more WOWs!&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Most tools above are available via NPM modules.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alternative to Gulp.js, such as webpack, yarn, and bash scripts&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It seems though built process are always evolving and we constantly have to change tools, thats why I am considering either consolidating my Gulp.js workflow to Webpack or author a simple built script.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;building-my-own-front-end-workflow-theme&quot;&gt;Building my own Front-End Workflow Theme&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda figure I needed a codebase to collect solutions to common web problems that a CSS Framework was not able to accomodate. And also, to fit specifications of a project. So I decided to start a theme project called Front-End Flow (FEF) theme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Delving deeper with Zurb Foundation&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Foundation is a great tool to start projects, I built my Gulp.js workflow to accomodate Zurb Foundation and other JavaScript framework/plugins.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;But it still lacks some solutions to common web problems.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I may need to update FEF repo documentation though to specify these common web problems I’ve come across.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SASS/CSS part is good but JavaScript part still needs re-coding and cleaning up&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;and converting my Gulp.js to Webpack or a bash script.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;JavaScript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These last 2 (JavaScript and FullStack/Ecommerce) are my favorite. This blog contains mostly about JavaScript concepts in theory, but this past year, I was able to put those theories in practice! I’m happy and glad I took the time to read and blog about JavaScript Interview Questions and took courses on FreeCodeCamp solving algorithms. I am 100% sure this is the route I want to go, JavaScript and becoming a Fullstack/Ecommerce developer!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coding animations or a JavaScript SPA application, either concepts, I know I will take advantage of further practicing my coding skills and understanding of Fullstack concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Demonstrated my JavaScript coding skills, creatively solving problems&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Authored code for a Personalization Platform&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Separated my JS code using ES6 import export feature&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction to React.js&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I wanted to organize my JavaScript code and modularize it.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Coming up with code snippets to different problems is hard and I think it is worth keeping those code snippets for future use. Thats why I want to take advantage of Web Components and I heard React.js is fully developed for this usage.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;fullstackecommerce&quot;&gt;Fullstack/Ecommerce&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was excited when I was able to build a simple contact form, submit it to MySQL database and display it on a Admin page. And also when I first started templating with Blade on Laravel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just using a MVC framework makes me think of possibilities I am able to build and how easy it is for me to be able to organize my code file structure and set naming conventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m starting to think I got this thing for Organization, cleanliness, and performance.
Anyways, below is a recap of what I’ve accomplished and what I want to tackle next:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic form submission and query data with PHP and MySQL&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This is the simple contact form and display of data.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learned Laravel, from templating to submitting form with AJAX&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learned how to setup Laravel&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Templating in Blade&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Storing and Querying data from JSON files rather than database. For performance purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learned how to use AJAX in submitting form in Laravel and storing it in database.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction to CRUD with Laravel&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;After having a glimpse and hands-on experience with Laravel, I was able to get an idea of how CRUD systems are structured in Laravel&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;yup! I want to build an Admin Dashboard where users are able to edit data coming from a JSON file.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;kinda like building my own Jekyll or Grav but flexible enough to accomodate database&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction to E-commerce system with plain PHP, Javascript&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I was given a chance to author code for a Personalization platform. I was quite challenged with this project, solving problems creatively.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;I’ve also learned how a JavaScript application is structured with an E-commerce system
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Adding to cart by storing values to PHP Session&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;Using Session to keep data throughout Edit page, Add To Cart modal, Cart item page, Checkout page, and last, Order confirmation.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there it is, after blogging a recap of what I’ve learned, I should be able to distinguish my next set of concepts/topics to learn and skills to have under my belt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;moving-forward&quot;&gt;Moving forward:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wordpress&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;start a sideline business, hopefully it works well&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Building FEF Theme&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;convert gulp.js to webpack or script&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;organize JS files&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;use web components&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JavaScript&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;code more, blog more on JS Interview Questions&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;look into testing, interaction of application and inputting sample information&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;exciting new projects to learn:
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;3d model product viewer&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;viewport scroll to snap then animation/transition starts&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FullStack/E-commerce&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Continue building an Admin Dashboard&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;the whole CRUD shibang!
and a mixture of static JSON data and database&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HTML5/CSS3&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;learn more about SVG&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;implement simple CSS3 transitions&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2017 08:29:22 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/New-stuff-to-learn</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/New-stuff-to-learn</guid>
        
        <category>3d</category>
        
        <category>webgl</category>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        <category>crud</category>
        
        <category>laravel</category>
        
        <category>parallax</category>
        
        <category>ecommerce</category>
        
        <category>wordpress</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Venturing into a Fullstack Framework with Laravel</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Date Published: Nov 11, 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, I feel like its time to venture out of Front-End Web Development and look into a Fullstack Framework. One of my favorite framework is Keystone.js. It is a Node.js Database-driven framework. But learning a framework based off of PHP is mandatory, and so I came across Laravel. I’m not going to necessarily drift away from Keystone.js. As a Front-End Web Developer, I love Javascript and I don’t think I am going to give the language up easily.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal is to master atleast 1 or 2 Fullstack framework that is based off of 2 different language, Keystone.js and Laravel, but this blog post will focus on Laravel with a bit of comparison with Keystone.js and discusses about some of the features of what comprises a small-large scale web applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m going back and forth with this blog post, writing my experience from choosing to mastering a framework, I’ve included a table of contents below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;table-of-contents&quot;&gt;Table of Contents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#comparison-chart&quot;&gt;Comparison chart: Keystone.JS and Laravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#learning-resources&quot;&gt;Learning Resources&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#getting-started-with-laravel&quot;&gt;Getting started with Laravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#understanding-laravels-front-end-workflow&quot;&gt;Understanding Laravel’s Front-End Workflow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#coding-templates-to-populating-static-data-from-json-file&quot;&gt;Coding templates to populating static data from JSON file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#from-static-data-to-implementing-a-database&quot;&gt;From Static data to implementing a Database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#simple-contact-form-sending-emails&quot;&gt;Simple Contact form, Sending Emails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#intro-to-create-in-crud&quot;&gt;Intro to Create in CRUD&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#method-for-creating-a-contact-form-to-storing-to-db&quot;&gt;Method for creating a contact form to storing in db&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#method-for-converting-static-data-in-template-to-json-object-value&quot;&gt;Method for converting static data in template to JSON object value&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#method-for-developing-a-project-from-scratch&quot;&gt;Method for developing a project from scratch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#defining-my-specs-for-a-custom-admin-panel&quot;&gt;Defining my specs for a custom Admin Panel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#building-a-cms-from-scratch&quot;&gt;Building a CMS from scratch&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;comparison-chart&quot;&gt;Comparison chart&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve also took the time to do research and write a comparison chart. Below is my researched with a high-level view of what features I look for in a framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keystone.js&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Laravel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt; &lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;http://keystonejs.com&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;https://laravel.com/docs/4.2/introduction&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Language&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Node.js&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;PHP&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Templating, Routing&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Swig, Jade, handlebars. Yes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Blade. Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;RESTful&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CRUD, Database&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes, MongoDB&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes, MySQL&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;ACL&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Authentication and Session Management&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;CMS&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Yes, Automatically generated Admin UI&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;No&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Code Readability&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Simple and Clean&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Simple and Clean&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Programming Style&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;MVC&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;MVC&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Server Maintenance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;NVM, easy switching of Nodejs versions in server, not too much dependencies&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Application Maintenance&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;NPM, manages versions of modules in application&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Security&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;no credentials or keys are stored in code, they are stored in a separate&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Documentation&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;apidoc.js&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;Community Support&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Active github repo, future releases, books, tutorials, opensource community&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;learning-resources&quot;&gt;Learning Resources&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I’m discovering Laravel and the whole PHP realm, I’ve discovered a site called &lt;a href=&quot;https://tutsplus.com/&quot;&gt;envatotuts+&lt;/a&gt; which carries Laravel tutorials from beginner to advance level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.tutsplus.com/courses/get-started-with-laravel-5&quot;&gt;Get Started with Laravel 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.tutsplus.com/courses/build-a-cms-with-laravel&quot;&gt;Build a CMS with Laravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and more, there are various tutorials that covers what we can do with Laravel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-started-with-laravel&quot;&gt;Getting started with Laravel&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I first created a github repo and followed the instructions for &lt;a href=&quot;https://laravel.com/docs/5.3/installation&quot;&gt;installing Laravel&lt;/a&gt; via Laravel Installer on my Mac.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;On my local, I just ran &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php artisan serve&lt;/code&gt; to start a development environment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Also take into consideration of Configuration. We also need to check for Directory permissions and Application Key.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;All of these information are available at &lt;a href=&quot;https://laravel.com/docs/5.3/installation&quot;&gt;https://laravel.com/docs/5.3/installation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tranferring your Laravel local code to an Ubuntu stage server was a bit of a challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;There were missing php dependencies, I had to collaborate with other developers to solve this issue.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set its Web Document Root to its &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/public&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.env.example&lt;/code&gt; file as &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt; file and run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php artisan key:generate&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were no problem with transferring our Application code, it was more of setting its environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;understanding-laravels-front-end-workflow&quot;&gt;Understanding Laravels’ Front-End Workflow&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Laravel comes with a default install of Bootstrap, Vue, SASS, Webpack, and uses Gulp.js to compile its assets, although, Laravel developed its own compiling tool which is built on top of Gulp.js called &lt;strong&gt;Laravel Elixir&lt;/strong&gt;. It is an NPM module and is defined in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;. Laravel also uses NPM to install the default Front-end packages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon readings its &lt;a href=&quot;https://laravel.com/docs/5.3/elixir&quot;&gt;documentation on Laravel Elixir&lt;/a&gt;, it seems like this tool makes it easy for developers to use Gulp.js. Though, the only drawback I forsee using Laravel Elixir is we can’t further customize our build process and we will depend on Laravel Elixir’s features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have a background with Front-End Development and I’ve growned accustomed to some front-end packages, I will be using my own &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rlynjb/frontendflow&quot;&gt;Front-End Workflow starterkit theme&lt;/a&gt;, instead re-installing NPM and Bower packages and redefining paths and build process in my Gulp.js file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;coding-templates-to-populating-static-data-from-json-file&quot;&gt;Coding templates to populating static data from JSON file&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a link to an a quick and simple overview of an MVC Application structure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://selftaughtcoders.com/from-idea-to-launch/lesson-17/laravel-5-mvc-application-in-10-minutes/&quot;&gt;Creating a Basic Laravel 5 MVC Application in 10 Minutes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;My method usually starts off with defining a route and creating a template file for that particular route.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next is store sample data inside of JSON file and load file in a Controller
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vegibit.com/creating-static-and-dynamic-web-pages-in-laravel/&quot;&gt;Creating Static And Dynamic Web Pages In Laravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://vegibit.com/json-in-laravel/&quot;&gt;http://vegibit.com/json-in-laravel/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;My rule is, if a website contains less than 15 or 20 items, keep it data static
But, if items grow to 20 or more AND will contain a CRUD method, then proceed with Database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;from-static-data-to-implementing-a-database&quot;&gt;From Static data to implementing a Database&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming from a front-end web development and a bit of MVC background, Database concepts was new to me. Although I did dabbled a bit into sql queries, its still different from having the knowledge of Database tools available we can use in a Fullstack framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Laravel, there are tools available that helps us manage our database. Features that came with Laravel are listed below with a bit of methodology when implementing a Database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;When we run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php artisan make:model User --migration&lt;/code&gt; to create a Database, Laravel assumes you configured your database settings on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;config/database.php&lt;/code&gt; file. The generated Model and Migration script files are not aware of its configuration settings.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To create a Database, run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php artisan make:model User --migration&lt;/code&gt; command. This will generate a &lt;strong&gt;Eloquent ORM Model&lt;/strong&gt; and a &lt;strong&gt;Migration&lt;/strong&gt; script.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Eloquent ORM&lt;/strong&gt; - Model allows us to easily query and insert data in our tables.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Migration&lt;/strong&gt; - Creates a Table; Builds our Database Schema; Preserves Database Schema, revision control&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Seeding
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;is a way to create data fast. It populates data into a Database Table.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sheepy85.wordpress.com/2014/09/19/database-seed-migration-in-laravel-5-0/&quot;&gt;https://sheepy85.wordpress.com/2014/09/19/database-seed-migration-in-laravel-5-0/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.fullstack4u.com/laravel/laravel-5-load-seed-data-from-json/&quot;&gt;http://www.fullstack4u.com/laravel/laravel-5-load-seed-data-from-json/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y0y3-m05Emc&quot;&gt;Understanding Database with Laravel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;simple-contact-form-sending-emails&quot;&gt;Simple Contact form, Sending emails&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are tons fo tutorials on the web about creating a conact form with Laravel but it doesn’t seem to explain the basics. The link below though,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.tutsplus.com/courses/get-started-with-laravel-5/lessons/sending-emails&quot;&gt;Sending Emails&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;seem to explain the simplest and plainest method of how we can implement a Contact form in Laravel using Route &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Route::get...&lt;/code&gt; and Mail Facade &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Mail::send...&lt;/code&gt;.
From this tutorial, we can further build our Contact form to use Controller for code separation and gather User input from Views. We will be able to store Contact form data in database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 2 ways to compose an email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Raw text&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;From a View&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;raw-text&quot;&gt;Raw Text&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a Route where we can send emails from.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define a Mail Facade and inside, define an instance of Illuminate Message to build mail properties.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sign up for Mailtrap.io and configure &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now, when we visit &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/contact&lt;/code&gt;, it should send test email defined inside of Mail facade.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mail should be sent in Raw format located under Raw tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Route::get(&#39;/contact&#39;, function() {
  // define a Mail facade
  Mail::raw(&#39;kirby this is a test&#39;, function($message) {
    /*
      inside we will have an instance of
      Illuminate\Mail\Message

      inside of this closure, we can set other prooerties of email
    */
    $message-&amp;gt;subject(&#39;testing&#39;)
            -&amp;gt;to(&#39;bill@mail.com&#39;)
            -&amp;gt;from(&#39;non@mail.com&#39;);
  });

  return &#39;email has been sent&#39;;
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;from-views-template&quot;&gt;From Views template&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define a Route again.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Instead of Mail Facade Raw &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Mail::raw...&lt;/code&gt;, we will use Mail Facade Send &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Mail:send...&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once URL is visited, it will send email to Mailtrap.io for test.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Mail should be sent in HTML format under HTML tab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;// this will get data from view or user input
Route::get(&#39;/contact/view&#39;, function() {

  //  param1 = path to view template
  //  param2 = array of data
  //  param3 = closure to setup message that we will be sending
  Mail::send(&#39;conact-view&#39;, [&#39;name&#39;=&amp;gt;&#39;Bob&#39;], function($message) {
    $message-&amp;gt;subject(&#39;testing&#39;)
            -&amp;gt;to(&#39;bill@mail.com&#39;)
            -&amp;gt;from(&#39;non@mail.com&#39;);
  });
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;intro-to-create-in-crud&quot;&gt;Intro to Create in CRUD&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are the resources I used in learning basic CRUD, form handling in Laravel, and AJAX form post.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://code.tutsplus.com/courses/get-started-with-laravel-5/lessons/handle-form-input&quot;&gt;Forms and Data Validation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://laracasts.com/discuss/channels/requests/laravel-5-cant-use-ajax-post-request&quot;&gt;Laravel 5 can’t use ajax post request&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/32718870/how-to-get-all-input-of-post-in-laravel-5&quot;&gt;How to get All input of POST in Laravel 5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://laravel.com/docs/5.4/database&quot;&gt;Database: Getting Started&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dealing-with-global-variables&quot;&gt;Dealing with Global variables&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/32942379/global-variable-in-laravel-controller&quot;&gt;Global variable in laravel controller&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/29715813/laravel-5-global-blade-view-variable-available-in-all-templates&quot;&gt;Laravel 5 - global Blade view variable available in all templates&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-for-creating-a-contact-form-to-storing-to-db&quot;&gt;Method for creating a Contact Form to storing to DB&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Template Contact form
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;include validation (Zurb Foundation Abide or HTML5 validation)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;include &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;name=&quot;&quot;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;maxlength=&quot;&quot;&lt;/code&gt; on input fields&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;include `` before Submit input button&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;provided by Laravel, a secure way to manage POST forms&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;include a Thank You and Error messages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Author JavaScript submit ajax code
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;include &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;e.preventDefault();&lt;/code&gt; to prevent page refresh&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on Ajax, serialize data coming in from form&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;input url POST data in defined in routes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define Routes
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;since we are posting, use POST instead of GET&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ex: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Route::post(&#39;/contact/create&#39;, &#39;ContactController@create&#39;);&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;define url and Controller and its public function that will handle database form submission and other logic associated with create task.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create Controller
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on root directory, run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php artisan make:controller ContactController&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;inside &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;ContactController.php&lt;/code&gt;, define facades&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ex: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;use DB;&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;use Illuminate\Support\Facades\Mail;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;inside its public function&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;assign form input values to variables
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;these are the fields defined in form&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;write code to store on database, ref: &lt;a href=&quot;https://laravel.com/docs/5.4/database&quot;&gt;https://laravel.com/docs/5.4/database&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;write code to send data to email, ref: &lt;a href=&quot;https://laravel.com/docs/5.4/mail&quot;&gt;https://laravel.com/docs/5.4/mail&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup database
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;go to phpmyadmin and create a database, enter credentials, and create a table&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;create columns and defined the ff.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;form fields&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;include ID: int, auto_increment, primary&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;include submitted_at: timestamp, current_timestamp&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;on &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt; file, configure database settings&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup Mailer
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;go to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.env&lt;/code&gt; file and input settings&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;we are using &lt;a href=&quot;#from-views-template&quot;&gt;From Views Template&lt;/a&gt; code&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;using Mail facade requires additional steps&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;create a Requests by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php artisan make:requests SendContact&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;inside SendContact.php, input the ff.
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;set authorize to true&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;input fields on rules function&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;create a template under &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;resources/views/emails/contact.blade.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to test, we can use our email address temporarily&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-for-converting-static-data-in-template-to-json-object-value&quot;&gt;Method for converting static data in template to JSON object value&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After templating
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;structure your JSON data with a template file values&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;use &lt;a href=&quot;http://jsoneditoronline.org&quot;&gt;http://jsoneditoronline.org&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;store file in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;database/data/nameoffile.json&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a Controller
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;run &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php artisan make:controller HomeController&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;define public function to contain logic for displaying data from JSON file&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;write code to load JSON file and loop through JSON value&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;and define template at the bottom along with passing &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$data&lt;/code&gt; from looped json file&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define Controller in Route
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;replace define function in route to point to controller and its public function&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;In HomeController, define variables and assign value for JSON file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;replace static data in templates to use variable from its controller&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Handle Exceptions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scotch.io/tutorials/creating-a-laravel-404-page-using-custom-exception-handlers&quot;&gt;https://scotch.io/tutorials/creating-a-laravel-404-page-using-custom-exception-handlers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;defining-my-specs-for-a-custom-admin-panel&quot;&gt;Defining my specs for a custom Admin Panel&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My admin panel specs are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;simple navigation (straightforward, simpler than wordpress)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;able to do CRUD unto json files&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;contains just fields or forms (simple)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;display contact form data from contact form fields&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;uses miminal text editor features with instructions
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;user will be using HTML tags&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;bold text&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;links&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;breakline/ new line&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;image or assets uploader and manager
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;contains fields for seo input (img alt, title)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;building-a-cms-from-scratch&quot;&gt;Building a CMS from scratch&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.kodecrash.com/javascript/read-write-json-file-using-php/&quot;&gt;Read-Write JSON file using PHP&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sitepoint.com/creating-a-scrud-system-using-jquery-json-and-datatables/&quot;&gt;Creating a SCRUD System Using jQuery, JSON and DataTables&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;method-for-developing-a-project-from-scratch&quot;&gt;Method for developing a project from scratch&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;setting-up-a-project&quot;&gt;Setting up a project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Setup Laravel, server, github repo, and configure FEF theme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;coding-a-theme-with-fef-theme&quot;&gt;Coding a theme with FEF Theme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rlynjb/frontendflow&quot;&gt;FEF Theme&lt;/a&gt; is my baby project. It includes my front end workflow with css framework and javascript plugins I often used. It also includes a collection of solutions to common interaction and browser compatibility issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code layout per page including UX.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;place image placeholders and text.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;determine responsiveness&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;determine user interaction of different components to be use&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code overall style, brand, typography&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Add in basic CSS3 transitions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;structuring-content-with-json&quot;&gt;Structuring Content with JSON&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Per page, define fields and determine if its content type, regular page, form, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Code fields into json file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Convert json files to be editable
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;modify Routing and Controllers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;modify Views to use data passed from json to Controllers&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 08 Feb 2017 02:58:47 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Venturing-into-a-fullstack-framework-with-Laravel</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Venturing-into-a-fullstack-framework-with-Laravel</guid>
        
        <category>php</category>
        
        <category>fullstack</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Using ES6 Modules in client-side</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I came into a halt where I need to split my JavaScript code. Prototyping an application, code can be done in one file but as it grows and add-on features are requested, lines of code will eventually increase. I’ve heard a few names of javascript module loaders, both for client and server. But what I really wanted to take advantage of is JavaScript’s new module feature, ‘ES6 Module’ &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;import&lt;/code&gt; &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;export&lt;/code&gt; (commonly used in Nodejs, server-side).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Projects I’ve been handling are focused on Front-End, so I need a module compiler for client-side. Most browsers still does not support ES6 Module feature, that’s why there are Client side JS module loaders available such as Browserify, Webpack, Rollup &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/19059580/client-on-node-uncaught-referenceerror-require-is-not-defined&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am still learning JavaScript modules but for simplicity, I’m going to use Browserify, Babel, and Gulp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a step-by-step scenario of how these tools are connected and how it transforms our ES6 code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We write code using ES6 capabilities inclduing (but not limited to) ES6 module loading.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Babelify translates this code to ES5-compatibility code with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; statements included.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Babelify is a Babel transformer for Browserify&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;ES5 code with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;require&lt;/code&gt; statements is transformed to the version that is fully understandable by browsers by Browserify&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://egorsmirnov.me/2015/05/25/browserify-babelify-and-es6.html&quot;&gt;ref&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional method….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gulp.js then compiles all dependencies and scripts and outputs the final (minified and compressed) javascript file.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A sample &lt;strong&gt;Gulp.js&lt;/strong&gt; task should look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;var gulp = require(&#39;gulp&#39;);
var browserify = require(&#39;browserify&#39;);
var babelify = require(&#39;babelify&#39;);
var source = require(&#39;vinyl-source-stream&#39;);

gulp.task(&#39;build&#39;, function () {
  return browserify({entries: &#39;./app.jsx&#39;, extensions: [&#39;.jsx&#39;], debug: true})
  .transform(babelify)
  .bundle()
  .pipe(source(&#39;bundle.js&#39;))
  .pipe(gulp.dest(&#39;dist&#39;));
});
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Side note&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m looking forward on taking advantage of what Babel plugins has to offer to replace Browserify and Babelify.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://babeljs.io/&quot;&gt;Babeljs.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://exploringjs.com/es6/ch_modules.html&quot;&gt;Exploringjs.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/19059580/client-on-node-uncaught-referenceerror-require-is-not-defined&quot;&gt;Client on node: Uncaught ReferenceError: require is not defined&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://egorsmirnov.me/2015/05/25/browserify-babelify-and-es6.html&quot;&gt;Browserify, Babelify and ES6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://babeljs.io/&quot;&gt;Babeljs.io&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://exploringjs.com/es6/ch_modules.html&quot;&gt;Exploringjs.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/32793404/es6-export-overwriting-function&quot;&gt;ES6 Export Overwriting Function&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 03:08:39 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Using-ES6-Modules-in-clientside</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Using-ES6-Modules-in-clientside</guid>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Getting Started with Magento Theming</title>
        <description>&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-starting-to-build-a-theme-in-magento2&quot;&gt;Before starting to build a theme in Magento2&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So before starting to build a theme, we need to know Magento 2’s architecture and status.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Magento 2 is extremely modularize (reminds me of Drupal)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it is based off of Zend Framework&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Alot of Major and Minor updates/changes in each version&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and foremost, it is Not practical to theme from scratch (trust me, I tried, unless you are a certified Magento 2 developer or someone willing to put in alot of time)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it comes with its own Front-End workflow (I think it uses Grunt, Less)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although, from all the learning curves listed above, Magento 2 is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a really secure Ecommerce system&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It has everything you need to immediately setup an online store&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;theming maybe tough, alot of overriding of templates (but we will try to keep CSS and JS minimal and will use our own &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rlynjb/frontendflow&quot;&gt;Front-end workflow&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;setting-up-a-child-theme&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Setting up a Child Theme&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once Magento 2 is installed&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Enable Development Mode &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo php bin/magento deploy:mode:set developer&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;ref: &lt;a href=&quot;http://magento.stackexchange.com/questions/13125/how-do-i-set-developer-mode-in-magento-2&quot;&gt;How di u set developer mode in magento2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a directory in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/app/design/frontend/&amp;lt;company name&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;theme name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy Magento 2 blank theme &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/vendor/magento/theme-frontend-blank/&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/app/design/frontend/&amp;lt;company name&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;theme name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rename all theme titles and names in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;composer.json&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;registration.php&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;theme.xml&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;theme.xml&lt;/code&gt; add &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;parent&amp;gt;Magento/blank&amp;lt;/parent&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Login to admin to change theme and clear-cache
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;locate admin URL in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/etc/config.php&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;create-a-template-for-a-page&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a template for a page&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Define a new page layout in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;layouts.xml&lt;/code&gt; by copy &amp;amp; pasting a column tag&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;1column.xml&lt;/code&gt; and rename to the name of page, ex. &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;homepage.xml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to admin and set a page to use new page layout defined&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clear cache in admin configuration page or cli &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php bin/magento cache:flush&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a template &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.phtml&lt;/code&gt; inside of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/templates&lt;/code&gt; directory and use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;block&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; tag inside of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;homepage.xml&lt;/code&gt; file to point to the template file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;override-magento-2-core-templates&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Override Magento 2 core templates&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow Magento 2 front end developer guide&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Copy &amp;amp; paste codebase from Magento 2 github repo&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tips:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analyze layout first&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look at default modules under &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;app/code/Magento&lt;/code&gt; files and reference in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Magento_Theme&lt;/code&gt; base templates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;loading-front-end-flow-assets&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Loading Front-End flow assets&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After loading Front-End flow assets files, we will comment out unnecessary Blank theme styles. This is a matter of inspecting unnecessary styles and commenting it out from its default &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.less&lt;/code&gt; files&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Comment out Magento 2’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;imports&lt;/code&gt; in its root &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/web/css/*.less&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;web/css/styles-m.less&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;web/css/_styles.less&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;web/css/source/_sources.less&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, we will keep Magento 2 Blank theme’s Grid system and remove its theme styles. Go back and forth to files above to remove styles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;recompile-default-blank-theme-styles-and-new-front-end-flow-styles&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Recompile default Blank theme styles and new Front-End flow styles&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delete static files
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rm -rf pub/static/frontend/&amp;lt;company name&amp;gt;/&amp;lt;theme name&amp;gt;/*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rm -rf var/cache/*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rm -rf var/page_cache/*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;rm -rf var/view_preprocessed/*&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Redeploy static files
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php bin/magento setup:static-content:deploy&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php bin/magento cache:clean&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;php bin/magento cache:flush&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo chown -R 777 /var&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;credential-requirements&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Credential Requirements&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As stated in its document, Secure keys do not use the normal Magento2 Marketplace username and password, rather&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once logged in, generate public and private keys
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;username is Public key&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;password is Private key&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Need to sign up a Magento Marketplace account to take advantage of their features or add-ons that can be install via composer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-docker-way&quot;&gt;The Docker way&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Installing manually was tedious so I’ve decided to use install Magento 2 via Docker and Docker Compose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To get a glimpse of how Docker and Docker Compose works, I’ved jotted down notes here: &lt;a href=&quot;Notes-on-creating-a-convenient-local-development-workflow-with-Docker&quot;&gt;Notes on creating a convenient Local Development Workflow with Docker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a sample &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file that installs Magento 2 &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mageinferno/magento2-docker-compose&quot;&gt;maginferno - magento2-docker-compose&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grab a copy of Magento 2 files as well &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/magento/magento2.git&quot;&gt;Github - Magento&lt;/a&gt; and place it on your &lt;strong&gt;host&lt;/strong&gt; and mount the necessary directories and files unto your &lt;strong&gt;docker container&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 03:14:55 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Getting-started-with-Magento-Theming</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Getting-started-with-Magento-Theming</guid>
        
        <category>cms</category>
        
        <category>ecommerce</category>
        
        <category>magento2</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Notes on creating a convenient Local Development Workflow with Docker</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;While working on a project that requires a new install of PHP and MySql, I came into a halt. It took me a day to re-configure my local development environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then came across Docker. With this research and learning a new technology. My goal is to establish an efficient local development workflow with Docker as I did with creating &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rlynjb/frontendflow&quot;&gt;Front-End Workflow Theme&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This article &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.airpair.com/docker/posts/efficiant-development-workfow-using-git-submodules-and-docker-compose&quot;&gt;Efficient development workflow using Git submodules and Docker Compose&lt;/a&gt; gave me a brief overview of what Docker and Git is capable of when architecturing your preferred local development, though, I did have to do further reading on my own to grasp Docker Engine, Docker Compose, and Git submodule (I will not be tackling this topic as I’m focus on Dockerfile and Docker Compose).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-far-what-i-know-about-docker-in-regards-of-hands-on-experience-is&quot;&gt;So far, what I know about Docker in regards of hands-on experience is&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we edit or create our source code in a directory from our local machine.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;to run the app
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;we use Docker to start images we define in &lt;strong&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Docker automatically creates a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://localhost&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;http://0.0.0.0&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Docker uses Port for each contained apps or websites&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;collections-of-tutorials&quot;&gt;Collections of tutorials&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;install &lt;strong&gt;Docker&lt;/strong&gt; via its official site &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.docker.com/docker-for-mac/&quot;&gt;Getting Started with Docker for Mac&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;useful-commands-and-info&quot;&gt;Useful commands and info&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look into &lt;strong&gt;Dockerfile&lt;/strong&gt; file references&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Look into &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file references and commandline references&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To access a container via terminal:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://askubuntu.com/questions/505506/how-to-get-bash-or-ssh-into-a-running-container-in-background-mode&quot;&gt;How to get bash or ssh into a running container in background mode?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo docker exec -i -t 665b4a1e17b6 /bin/bash #by ID&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sudo docker exec -i -t loving_heisenberg /bin/bash #by Name&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to start a containter &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose up&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose up -d&lt;/code&gt; to detach from status&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;to see processes: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker ps&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;run a command inside container from host
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker exec &amp;lt;container_id&amp;gt; &amp;lt;command&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-app-sample-workflow&quot;&gt;For App sample workflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.docker.com/compose/gettingstarted&quot;&gt;Practice Workflow with Docker compose&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-cms-sample-workflow&quot;&gt;For CMS sample workflow&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://visible.vc/engineering/docker-environment-for-wordpress/&quot;&gt;Practice Workflow with CMS using Docker compose&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; you have to be familiar with CMS directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We mount local directories from our machine to its Docker container/server with the use of &lt;strong&gt;volume&lt;/strong&gt; in its &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;docker-compose.yml&lt;/code&gt; file&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; we can have a copy of CMS install locally on out directory and mount it on Docker container/server&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2016 06:31:20 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Notes-on-creating-a-convenient-local-development-workflow-with-Docker</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Notes-on-creating-a-convenient-local-development-workflow-with-Docker</guid>
        
        <category>workflow</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Breaking down Cross-Browser Testing</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Below is my note on an article on smashing magazine. Article is mostly theory but I tried to take in the important info.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;two-main-objectives&quot;&gt;Two Main Objectives&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discovering bugs
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Entails trying to break your app to find bugs to fix.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Sanity-checking
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Involves verifying that majority of your audience receives the expected experience.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;know-your-statistics&quot;&gt;Know your Statistics&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Audience statistics&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Browser usage statistics&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;simplify-your-browser-usage-statistics&quot;&gt;Simplify your browser usage statistics&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Desktop Browsers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;we don’t care about:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;versions except IE&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;OS&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;same argument applies with Portable Browsers&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;new wave of browsers called: In-App browsers - browsers in social media platforms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Portable Browsers&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;whats important:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;version of the native Android browser used&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;version of iOS a device is running
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;very relevant as Safari versions are intrinsically linked to iOS&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;three-phase-attack&quot;&gt;Three-Phase Attack&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reconnaissance: Find Browser-Agnostic Bugs&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try resizing to view responsiveness. Was there a funky breakpoint anywhere?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Zoom in and out. Have the background-positions of your image sprite been knocked askew?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;See how the application behaves with Javascript turned off. Do you still get the core content?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;See how the application looks with CSS turned off. Do the semantics of the markup still make sense?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try turning both Javascript and CSS off. Are you getting an acceptable experience?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try interacting with the application using only your keyboard. Is it possible to navigate and see all the content?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Try throttling your connection and see how quickly the application loads. How heavy is the page load?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Raid: Test in High-Risk Browsers First&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Statistical Analysis of Bug Distribution&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;High-Risk are IE browsers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Medium-Rish are Safari, Opera&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Low-Rish are Chrome, Firefox&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Fixing bugs in bad browsers makes your code more resilient in good browsers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Identifying problematic browsers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://caniuse.com&quot;&gt;CanIUse&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;VirtualBox&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Check on actual device or browser&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Tools to rectify major compatibility issues:&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://modernizr.com&quot;&gt;Modernizr&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clearance: sanity checking&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;By this stage, we should be 80:20&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Figuratively, we’ve fixed 80% of the bugs after testing 20% of the browsers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Now, we verify the experience of 80% of audience through testing a different 20% of browsers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Prioritize the browsers&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Use a 3rd-party service that checks on multiple browsers and device&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2016/02/high-impact-minimal-effort-cross-browser-testing/&quot;&gt;High Impact, Minimal-Effort Cross-Browser Testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 05:57:02 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Breaking-down-cross-browser-testing</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Breaking-down-cross-browser-testing</guid>
        
        <category>testing</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Learning React</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;implementing react.js on gulp
- do a gulp task of react.js build&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*JSX makes us write HTML syntax in Javascript files&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;this does not run in browsers thats why we need a transpiler&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;since i am usin gulp, we are going to search for a gulp plugin that transpiles JSX files to plain js files&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;JSX to JS using babel&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;configuring gulp plugin babel was a bit tricky due to NPM dependency issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;learning react is quite overwhelming. I think with any new front-end is overwhelming due to the amount of dependencies or tools options that are available. Front-end development has indeed bloom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;before digging further into random articles that suggests to use this or that tool. I’ve decided to learn plain React.js. Stripping other unknown tools and focusing on the foundation, then once comfortable with plain React.js, move on to another tool and implement. Learning indeed can also be a step-by-step process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jamesknelson.com/learn-raw-react-no-jsx-flux-es6-webpack/&quot;&gt;Learn Raw React — no JSX, no Flux, no ES6, no Webpack&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.risingstack.com/the-react-way-getting-started-tutorial/&quot;&gt;The React.js Way: Getting Started Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://buildwithreact.com/&quot;&gt;Build with React&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2016 03:58:40 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Learning-React</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Learning-React</guid>
        
        <category>javascript</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Front-End Design Specs</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;determing a workflow is hard but its even harder when we go through a laborious iterative process with designers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;since i have been using Zurb foundation, zurb foundation comes with a settings file that defines global variables for general design settings. This gave me the idea that responsive web design follows a certain pattern, same as Development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;process to determing on refining the design and developer workflow are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;list down general design css properties
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;layout
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;max-width&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;number of columns grid&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;gutter width
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;small breakpoint&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;medium breakpoint&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;typography - header
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;header font&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;header font sizes
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;small breakpoint&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;medium breakpoint&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;header color&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;header alignment, leading, kerning&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;header opacity, filter&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;header font weight&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;typography - body
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;body font size
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;small breakpoint&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;medium breakpoint&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;body font color&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;body font family&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;body line height, leading, kerning&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;body font weight&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;spacing measurement
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;width and height
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;small breakpoint&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;medium breakpopint&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;large breakpoint&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;spacing bet object and canvas&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;spacing bet multiple objects&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;spacing bet text and objects&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;objects
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;fill color&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;stroke, color, size, style&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;opacity/filter&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;corner radius&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;color palette
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;primary, secondary, tertiary, quaternary&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;monotone
            &lt;ul&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;gray - light, medium, dark&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;black&lt;/li&gt;
              &lt;li&gt;white&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;/ul&gt;
          &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;after analyzing above data and visually looking at a design comp, these properties are already set on the provided design comp but not documented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;this is where PNG Express comes in, photoshop plugin tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;after testing on a design comp and implementing it on theme development, it is indeed an ease for us developers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so overview process would be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;designer designs ui comp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;after design is complete, designer sets Design Specs with PNG Express&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;pass the UI comp with design specs to front end developer&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;front end developer implements these measurements on css styles sheets&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;it does not need to be exact pixels, this is a good way to atleast get an estimate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;with this in set, this also gives Front end developers to compile a Style Guide and or components that can be resuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smashingmagazine.com/2014/10/front-end-development-ode-to-specifications/&quot;&gt;A Front-End Developer’s Ode To Specifications&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pngexpress.com/&quot;&gt;PNG Express&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jul 2016 03:58:40 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Front-End-Design-Specs</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Front-End-Design-Specs</guid>
        
        <category>workflow</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Front-End Workflow with Grav theme</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This blog post explains on how I have setup a custom basic Grav theme with modern front-end workflow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This idea have come into mind when I was assigned a project that requires the use of a CSS framework and other plugins for animations/transitions. Since I will be building websites with the same requirements, why not create a &lt;strong&gt;Grav Starter Theme with Front-End Workflow&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be updating this theme with tested CSS animations/transitions plugins that I think will play well with Grav and meets client’s business requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For documentation and updates, refer to its github repo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rlynjb/gravtheme-frontendflow&quot;&gt;Grav Theme - Front-End Flow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#before-starting&quot;&gt;Before starting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#every-website-project-will-have&quot;&gt;Every website project will have&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#developing-starter-kit-theme&quot;&gt;Developing starter kit theme&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#gulpfilejs-setup&quot;&gt;gulpfile.js setup&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#importing-foundation-components-and-overriding-settings-file&quot;&gt;importing foundation components and overriding settings file&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;before-starting&quot;&gt;Before starting:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install the following globally as it is required to run Bower and Gulp in your local dev.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Node&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;NPM or NVM if you deal with multiple node versions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After installing Grav
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;refer to ff. link for Getting Started with Grav: &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;git clone&lt;/code&gt; this repo inside of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/user/themes/&lt;/code&gt; directory&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;inside of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/user/themes/gravtheme-frontendflow/&lt;/code&gt; directory, run:
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;npm install -g&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;required to run Bower and Gulp&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bower install&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;installs 3rd-party plugins used on this theme&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gulp &amp;amp;&amp;amp; gulp watch&lt;/code&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;builds our sass files. We’ve carefully chose each Foundation components to avoid CSS bloats and overriding of styles.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;every-website-project-will-have&quot;&gt;Every website project will have:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grav + Admin core&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;To get fresh install: &lt;a href=&quot;https://getgrav.org/&quot;&gt;Get Grav&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Basic Grav Theme setup&lt;/strong&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Follow tutorial to get started: &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/themes/theme-tutorial&quot;&gt;Get Grav - Theme Tutorial&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt; file
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;installs &lt;strong&gt;Bower&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Gulp.js&lt;/strong&gt;, and other gulp dependencies for build system and front-end workflow aid&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;go to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npmjs.com/&quot;&gt;npmjs.com&lt;/a&gt; to search for more packages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bower.json&lt;/code&gt; file
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;installs required 3rd-party assets&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;go to &lt;a href=&quot;http://bower.io&quot;&gt;bower.io&lt;/a&gt; to search for more packages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;or install packages via &lt;strong&gt;Github repos&lt;/strong&gt;
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bower.io/docs/api/&quot;&gt;bower.io - api&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/19348076/installing-a-dependency-with-bower-from-url-and-specify-version&quot;&gt;Installing a dependency with Bower from URL and specify version&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;setup &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gulpfile.js&lt;/code&gt; file
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Why use &lt;strong&gt;Gulp.js&lt;/strong&gt;?
        &lt;ul&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sass&lt;/strong&gt; seem to not support building multiple &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;scss&lt;/code&gt; files. It require either Compass, Grunt, or libsass (same Build system concept as Gulp.js)&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Grav’s Asset Manager&lt;/strong&gt; lacks support for sass and its still quite buggy&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Check this project’s github repo for &lt;strong&gt;package.json&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;bower.json&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;gulp.js&lt;/strong&gt; updates.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rlynjb/gravtheme-frontendflow&quot;&gt;Grav Theme - Front-End Flow&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;developing-starter-kit-theme&quot;&gt;Developing starter kit theme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During developing &lt;strong&gt;Grav Theme - Front-End Flow&lt;/strong&gt; starter kit theme, I have come across issues that I think worth noting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gulpfilejs-setup&quot;&gt;gulpfile.js setup&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After installing &lt;strong&gt;foundation-sites&lt;/strong&gt; via bower. we will need to setup our &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gulpfile.js&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Follow the youtube video tutorial to get started:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/De6H0eFrfvY&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;importing-foundation-components-and-overriding-settings-file&quot;&gt;importing foundation components and overriding settings file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While setting it up, I’ve come across an issue. The following link helped me solved the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/34537431/foundation-6-does-not-generate-any-styles&quot;&gt;stackoverflow - Foundation 6 does not generate any styles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another issue i came across was overriding Foundation’s settings file. It took me awhile until I figured out why its not overriding the default settings file. Solution is on my github repo&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/rlynjb/gravtheme-frontendflow&quot;&gt;GravTheme - Front End Flow theme&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 05:09:47 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Front-End-Workflow-with-Grav-theme</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Front-End-Workflow-with-Grav-theme</guid>
        
        <category>static site</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Getting started and basic theming with Grav</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi all! I’ve created this blog post as my notes for learning and exploring Grav. If you haven’t heard, Grav is a full flat-file CMS, this means, it does not use any database. All data are saved as YAML files. It follows a certian naming convention and uses its directory page hierarchy structure to generate routes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, consider this blog post as notes rather than re-explaining informations that exists on Grav documentation or other blog sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Contents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#getting-started-on-digital-ocean&quot;&gt;Getting Started on Digital Ocean&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;create a droplet&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;debugging nginx with php5-fpm&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;fixing php 502 gateway page&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;tips on using configuration files yaml&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#getting-started-on-mamp&quot;&gt;Getting Started on MAMP&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Install Brew&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Install MAMP&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Install Grav&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#theming-in-grav&quot;&gt;Theming in Grav&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Method for setting up a pre-made HTML5 template to Grav theme&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Method for loadings assets and partial out the main index.html file&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Breaking our home page template file further by using Modular Pages&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Creating custom fields to let users update data in theme by using Blueprint Pages&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-started-on-digital-ocean&quot;&gt;Getting Started on Digital Ocean&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;create-a-droplet&quot;&gt;create a droplet&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/hosting/vps/digitalocean&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/hosting/vps/digitalocean&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;debugging-nginx-with-php5-fpm&quot;&gt;debugging nginx with php5-fpm&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://serverfault.com/questions/562062/nginx-with-php-fpm-got-502-bad-gateway-on-ubuntu-server-12-04&quot;&gt;resource 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/1706111/where-can-i-find-the-error-logs-of-nginx-using-fastcgi-and-django&quot;&gt;resource 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fixing-php-502-gateway-page&quot;&gt;fixing php 502 gateway page&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/owncloud/core/issues/14187&quot;&gt;resource&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tips-on-using-configuration-files-yaml&quot;&gt;tips on using configuration files, yaml:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;do not change configs in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/system/config/system.yaml&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/system/config/site.yaml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;do not change configs in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/user/plugins/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;rather override them in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user/config/system.yaml&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user/config/site.yaml&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user/config/plugins/myplugin.yaml&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;note: all yaml files are contructed by name spacing. Grav picks it up in a hierarchy order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;getting-started-on-mamp&quot;&gt;Getting Started on MAMP&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;install-brew&quot;&gt;1. Install Brew&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is to install &lt;strong&gt;git&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;other development goodies&lt;/strong&gt; if you are a fan of commandline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://brew.sh/&quot;&gt;http://brew.sh/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://commandlinepoweruser.com/&quot;&gt;http://commandlinepoweruser.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;install-mamp&quot;&gt;2. Install MAMP&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can use any webserver but I’ve used &lt;strong&gt;MAMP&lt;/strong&gt; because it was the quickest way I can install a webserver and setup a &lt;strong&gt;local Apache&lt;/strong&gt; eventhough we are not using MySql database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mamp.info/en/&quot;&gt;https://www.mamp.info/en/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;install-grav&quot;&gt;3. Install Grav&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download &lt;strong&gt;Grav core + admin plugins&lt;/strong&gt; files from &lt;a href=&quot;https://getgrav.org/downloads&quot;&gt;https://getgrav.org/downloads&lt;/a&gt; and place into &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;htdocs&lt;/code&gt; directory.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can choose either &lt;strong&gt;Grav core&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Grav core + admin plugins&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;If &lt;strong&gt;Grav core&lt;/strong&gt; only, you have the option to install &lt;strong&gt;Grav admin&lt;/strong&gt; later by running &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;bin/gpm install admin&lt;/code&gt; on the root directory of your &lt;strong&gt;Grav core&lt;/strong&gt; files.&lt;br /&gt;
 More info: &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/admin-panel/introduction&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/admin-panel/introduction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unzip the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;grav-admin-v*.*.**.zip&lt;/code&gt; file on the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;htdocs&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can rename the &lt;strong&gt;Grav&lt;/strong&gt; directory to whatever project name you want.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;You can also move the &lt;strong&gt;Grav core files&lt;/strong&gt; to an empty &lt;strong&gt;Github Repo directory&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure to move &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.htaccess&lt;/code&gt; file as well to avoid &lt;strong&gt;404 Not Found&lt;/strong&gt; error when visiting subpages.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For more info, check &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/troubleshooting&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/troubleshooting&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://getgrav.org/&quot;&gt;https://getgrav.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;theming-in-grav&quot;&gt;Theming in Grav&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-for-setting-up-a-pre-made-html5-template-to-grav-theme&quot;&gt;Method for setting up a pre-made HTML5 template to Grav theme&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Unzip the &lt;strong&gt;HTML5 theme&lt;/strong&gt; zip file unto the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user/themes/&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Register your theme by following &lt;strong&gt;Step 1 - Base Theme Setup&lt;/strong&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/themes/theme-tutorial&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/themes/theme-tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;Step 1 - Base Theme Setup&lt;/strong&gt; - #2&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;Tip:&lt;/em&gt; You can use the same HTML5 theme directory name or you can clean up directory name by renaming and practicing proper naming convention.&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;Ex:&lt;/em&gt; Avoid whitespace, avoid special characters except &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;_&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;-&lt;/code&gt; following &lt;em&gt;camel case or snake case&lt;/em&gt; naming convention.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;Step 1 - Base Theme Setup&lt;/strong&gt; - #3&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;Tip:&lt;/em&gt; I chose to follow &lt;strong&gt;Grav’s Theme directory structure&lt;/strong&gt; rather than to use the &lt;strong&gt;HTML5 theme&lt;/strong&gt; default directory structure to avoid nested directory level, plus, Grav runs a &lt;em&gt;gpm&lt;/em&gt; engine which goes through each directories and yaml files to read data.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;Step 1 - Base Theme Setup&lt;/strong&gt; - #4&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;Tip:&lt;/em&gt; I believe this basically tells Grav that we are extending a Grav Theme class and our custom theme gets registered unto Grav core files.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;For &lt;strong&gt;Step 1 - Base Theme Setup&lt;/strong&gt; - #5&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;em&gt;Tip:&lt;/em&gt; This file just enables our theme, but later on, there are more theme configuration that uses this file.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;method-for-loading-assets-and-partial-out-the-main-indexhtml-file&quot;&gt;Method for loading assets and partial out the main index.html file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have setup our theme directory structures and registered our theme to Grav core files. We will continue on by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Load assets (css, js, images) in Head and Body tags.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction to using Twig templating engine.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Organize our code in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;index.html&lt;/code&gt; file by using Grav’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/templates/partials&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Now, we load our assets by moving HTML5 theme assets to Grav theme’s asset directory structure. Ex: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/css&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/fonts&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/images&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/js&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;/templates&lt;/code&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This step is a replacement for &lt;strong&gt;Step 2 - Add Bootstrap&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
 We are not using Boostrap, instead we are using the HTML5’s assets.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next is to just follow the remaining steps, &lt;strong&gt;Step 3 - Base Template&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;Step 8 - Testing&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;This step pretty much explains:&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;Loading assets.&lt;/strong&gt; When to use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;theme_url&lt;/code&gt; twig variable and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;do assets.add(&#39;&#39;)&lt;/code&gt; twig function and how it relates with &lt;strong&gt;Grav’s Asset Manager&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;br /&gt;
 &lt;strong&gt;Introduction to basic Twig syntax.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br /&gt; Also, exploring some of Grav’s global twig variables.
 &lt;strong&gt;Partial out&lt;/strong&gt; the theme’s header section, footer section, and main content section to maintain a cleaner &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;base.html.twig&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breaking-our-home-page-template-file-further-by-using-modular-pages&quot;&gt;Breaking our home page template file further by using Modular Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most HTML5 themes comes with a home page designed similar to one-page website designs. For this step, we are going to breakdown this one-page website design into sections and use &lt;strong&gt;Grav’s Modular Pages&lt;/strong&gt; templating to separate and organize these sections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;base.html.twig&lt;/code&gt; template and analyze what HTML tag is used to contain contents of each sections.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Tip:&lt;/em&gt; Usual container tags are &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;section&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/section&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;div id=&quot;&quot;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/div&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After determining the HTML tag container, convert these sections into &lt;strong&gt;Grav’s Modular Pages&lt;/strong&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Learn more about Modular Pages on the ff. link and ff. instructions: &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/content/modular&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/content/modular&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;It is also a good idea to scheme through &lt;strong&gt;Grav’s Content&lt;/strong&gt; documentation page &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/content&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/content&lt;/a&gt; to get a glimpse of the parts of a page.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;creating-custom-fields-to-let-users-update-data-in-theme-by-using-blueprint-pages&quot;&gt;Creating custom fields to let users update data in theme by using Blueprint Pages&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve broken our template further by each sections using &lt;strong&gt;Modular Pages&lt;/strong&gt;. What if we wanted users to update contents or bits pieces of data in each section using &lt;strong&gt;Grav’s Administration Panel&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this step, we will use Grav’s Forms called Blueprints &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/forms/blueprints&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/forms/blueprints&lt;/a&gt; to convert &lt;strong&gt;static data&lt;/strong&gt; into editable ones using Grav’s &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Admin dashboard &amp;gt; Pages&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an overview and how to setup a &lt;strong&gt;Themes and Plugins Blueprints&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;Pages Blueprints&lt;/strong&gt;, go to this link &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/forms/blueprints&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/forms/blueprints&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My experience with setting up Blueprints for &lt;strong&gt;Theme&lt;/strong&gt; configuration page and for each &lt;strong&gt;Modular Pages&lt;/strong&gt; was quite challenging. Grav’s documentation doesn’t seem to provide detailed information on &lt;strong&gt;how to define a field and which directory its information is stored&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although for &lt;strong&gt;Theme Blueprint&lt;/strong&gt; it was pretty straight forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;blueprints.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file in the root directory of theme.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Follow the &lt;strong&gt;Components of a Blueprint&lt;/strong&gt; in &lt;a href=&quot;https://learn.getgrav.org/forms/blueprints&quot;&gt;https://learn.getgrav.org/forms/blueprints&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; a YAML file will be generated for Theme configuration page in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;user/config&lt;/code&gt; directory.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was trial and error for &lt;strong&gt;Modular Page Blueprints&lt;/strong&gt; because its documentation seem to lack information on &lt;strong&gt;how to define a field and which directory its information is stored&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An overview method I find when working with Modular Page Blueprints are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;blueprints&lt;/code&gt; directory under root template directory &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;yourtheme &amp;gt; blueprints&lt;/code&gt;.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Since we are creating a blueprint for modular pages, we are going to store our blueprints (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.yaml&lt;/code&gt; files) under modular directory.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;So with this, create a modular directory under &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;yourtheme &amp;gt; blueprints &amp;gt; modular&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;some-modular-template-name.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file that pertains to a modular template.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tip:&lt;/strong&gt; Make sure your &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file name matches a Modular template name you want to create Admin custom fields for.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When defining &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.yaml&lt;/code&gt; file form, a good example would be the default &lt;strong&gt;Grav antimatter theme&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/getgrav/grav-theme-antimatter/blob/develop/blueprints/modular/showcase.yaml&quot;&gt;https://github.com/getgrav/grav-theme-antimatter/blob/develop/blueprints/modular/showcase.yaml&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Also, an additional note to keep in mind when working with Page Blueprints&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grav reads data in &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;*.yaml&lt;/code&gt; files in sequence of how directories and files are structured, So when defining a field, it needs to be under a parent &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;header.&lt;/code&gt; because blueprint pages store its data in pages headers. Also when uploading media files, Grav stores these media files under its page direcotory.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 03:52:08 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Getting-started-and-basic-theming-with-Grav</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://rlynjb.github.io/wandrr/Getting-started-and-basic-theming-with-Grav</guid>
        
        <category>static site</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
